A Finding Aid to the Don Eddy and Leigh Behnke Papers, 1966-2009, in the Archives of American Art AAA.eddydon
Archives of American Art
Don Eddy and Leigh Behnke papers
1966-2009
AAA.eddydon
Archives of American Art
7.2 Linear feet
The Don Eddy and Leigh Behnke papers, 1966-2009, measure 7.2 linear feet. Photographic materials, printed material, and writings document the realist painters' work, working methods, and exhibitions. Also found are subject files, some professional correspondence and personal photographs.
Eddy, Don
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Don Eddy and Leigh Behnke in 2009.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Don Eddy (b. 1944) and Leigh Behnke (b. 1946) are realist painters in New York City. They are married and both teach at the School of Visual Arts. Eddy is one of the thirteen original Photorealists.
Don Eddy was born in Long Beach, California. From around age ten until he left home to attend college, he worked at his father's auto body shop and became proficient in airbrush technique and color matching paint. Eddy studied with Jean Charlot at the University of Hawaii (B.F.A. 1967, M.F.A. 1969). His early paintings employed pictorial illusion and their subject matter came from material culture; part-time work as a tourist photographer in Honolulu prompted him to experiment with and think deeply about photography, leading him to the style that would come to be known as Photorealism. He was first recognized for paintings of automobiles done in acrylic using the spray technique learned at the auto body shop. From the 1970s and well into the next decade, Eddy's work was object oriented. Later, he produced "dream" paintings that included details from Old Master paintings, floating objects that introduced psychological elements and perceptual challenges. Over the next decade he simplified his imagery by pursuing still life and nature painting with complex, layered surfaces. Using photographs he takes himself as source material, Eddy continues to paint urban and nature scenes and has developed elaborate procedures for underpainting and overpainting. He teaches at the School of Visual Arts and is represented by Nancy Hoffman Gallery, New York.
Leigh Behnke, a native of Hartford, Connecticut, moved to New York City to attend Pratt Institute (B.F.A. 1969) and later studied at New York University (M.A. 1976). Behnke paints in oil and watercolor using her own photographs and digital images as source material. Interests in architecture, interiors, history, memory, nature, and scientific concepts are reflected in her work. She combines images and employs multi panels (diptych and polyptych) as a device for focusing on perception and pictorial space, commenting on images, and redefining subjects from other vantage points. Behnke has taught at the School of Visual Arts since 1979. She is represented by Fischbach Gallery, New York, and Plus One Gallery, London.
Scope and Content Note
The Don Eddy and Leigh Behnke papers, 1966-2009, measure 7.2 linear feet. Photographic materials, printed material, and writings document the realist painters' work, working methods, and exhibitions. Also found are subject files, some professional correspondence, and personal photographs.
Don Eddy's papers consist largely of photographic materials, writings, and printed material. Photographic materials include images of completed work and a significant amount of source material that documents Eddy's working methods. Also found are exhibition installation views, personal and travel pictures. Writings include a dissertation and two theses in which he figures prominently. Most printed material mentions Eddy or contains reproductions of his work.
The papers of Leigh Behnke, less voluminous than her husband's, are comprised mainly of photographic materials, printed material, and subject files. Among the photographic materials are images that served as source material and document her working methods. All printed material mentions Behnke or contains reproductions of her work. Subject files document projects, exhibitions, and miscellaneous topics.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series:
Series 1: Don Eddy papers, 1966-2009 (Boxes 1-6, 9-10; 5.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Leigh Behnke papers, 1974-2009 (Boxes 6-9; 1.4 linear feet)
Behnke, Leigh, 1946-; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting from photographs; Photo-realism; Photographs; Writings
- Don Eddy papers, 1966-2009; Series 1; 5.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-6, 9-10
  Scope and Contents note
  The papers of Don Eddy include a variety of materials that document the realist painter's work, working methods, exhibitions, and his place in the history of Photorealism.
  Biographical notes in a small notebook include chronological lists of all schools attended since kindergarten, employment history, and exhibition record; the same volume includes financial notes, names and addresses. Other financial records, also in a small notebook, record travel expenses. Family material concerns the memorial service for his father-in-law, AllenFrederick Behnke, at which Eddy spoke. Interviews may have been conducted as research for articles. Correspondence with Leda Cempellin concerns her writings and reserch about Eddy. Writings include an article and two theses about Eddy. Subject files concern arrangements by Galerie M. E. Thelen to exhibit Eddy's work at 5 venues in Germany, including "Documenta 5" (1972); and a surprise gift from artists to commemorate the Nancy Hoffman Gallery's 20th anniversary.
  Printed material consists mainly of catalogs from Eddy's group and solo exhibitions and periodicals containing articles, reviews, and reproductions. The few printed items that do not mention Eddy concern Photorealism, friends or students. Books include: Conversazioni con Don Eddy/Converstions with Don Eddy by Leda Cempellin; Don Eddy: The Resonance of Realism in the Art of Postwar America by Virginia Anne Bonito; and L'imperrealismo "Fotographica" Americano in pittura: Rizonanze storiche nells East e nella West Coast. Miscellaneous printed items include reproductions of artwork by Eddy, newsletters, and a press kit concerning his 2000 solo exhibition at Duke University Museum of Art.
  Artwork dates from the period when Eddy was studying at the University of Hawaii. His sketchbook contains mostly pencil drawings and includes some notes and brief writings. Photographs - along with some digital images, negatives, and 35-mm color slides - are mainly photographs taken by Eddy for inspiration and reference use, sometimes accompanied by drawings and brief notes. In additon there are a few viees of people, travel, exhibition installations, and artwork by Eddy.
  - Biographical Notes, Financial Record, Membership Certificate, Family, circa 1960s-circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview Transcripts, Don Eddy with Rose Hartman and L.L., undated; 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Leda Cempellin, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Eddy, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings (Box 1)
    - Articles about Eddy, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dissertation, "I ruoli dell'iperrealismo Americano a Documenta 5, Kassel 1972" by Leda Cempellin (Universita degli studi Parma), 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Thesis, "Aspetti dell'iperrealismo Americano storica" by Leda Cempellin Universita degli studi di Padova), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Thesis, "Hvad er superriealismen? Omden ekstreme realism i billedkunsten 1965-1980" by Kristian Handberg (Aarhus Universitet, 2007) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Inventory Cards, circa 1969-1970s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subject File - Galerie M. E. Thelen, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subject File - Nancy Hoffman Gallery, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material (Box 1)
    - Books, 1964-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - Clippings, undated; 1969-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, 1970-2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1970s; 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19-23)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1970s-1990s; Oversized material housed in Box 9 (Box 2, Folder 1-19)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 2001-2009 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Items, circa 1973-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Periodicals, 1971-2006 (Box 3, Folder 5-19)
      Other Finding Aids note
      Oversized material housed in Box 9
  - Artwork - Drawings, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Artwork Mezzotint and 4 Etching plates, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographic Materials (Box 4)
    - People, 1966-circa 1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Travel Views, 1967-circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition Installation Views, 1968-1970; undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Artwork by Eddy (1967-2009), circa 1967-2009; Oversized material housed in Box 9 (Box 4, Folder 7-15)
    - Source Material, circa 1960s-circa 1980s; Oversized material housed in Box 10 (Box 4, Folder 16-25)
    - Source Material, circa 1970s-circa 2000s; Oversized material housed in Box 10 (Box 5, Folder 1-22)
    - Source Material, circa 1990s-circa 2000s; Oversized material housed in Box 10 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalogs from Box 1, Folders 19-23, Box 2, Folders 1-19, Box 3, Folders 1-3, 1994; 1972 (Box 9)
  - Oversized Periodical from Box 3, Folder 19, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Oversized Photographs of Artwork by Eddy (executed circa 1968-circa 1970s) from Box 4, Folders 7-15 (Box 9)
  - Oversized Photographs - Source Material from Box 4, Folders 16-25, Box 5, Folders 1-22, Box 6, Folders 1-7, circa 1970s-circa 2000s (Box 10)
- Leigh Behnke papers, 1974-2009; Series 2; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 6-9
  Leigh Behnke's papers document her professional career, work, and working methods. Biographical material conists of two brief interviews conducted by Leda Cempellin and Jeri Hise. Correspondence concerns exhibitions and reproduction permissions; also included is a letter of recommendaiton on behalf of Behnke. Writings by Behnke are artist's statements, some general and others concerning specific paintings. Also, there is a piece about representational painting that may be the text of an article or talk.
  Subject files consisting of correspondence, photographs, notes and printed material reflect Behnke's professional activities and interests. A few files might be source material. Printed material is mostly exhibition catalogs for Behnke's group shows. Periodicals include article, reveiws, and reprocutions of her work. In addition to a book and calendars reproducing her work, miscellaneous printed items include a notice of the "Mo' Ladies and Some Gents" 2008 swim team that included Leigh Behnke.
  Most of the photographs, digital images, slides and negatives served a source material for Behnke's paintings; some are accompanied by drawings and notes. There are also views of Leigh Behnke and Don Eddy, as well as images of her artwork.
  - Interview Transcripts, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Resumes, circa 1979-circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1979-2005 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Writings by Leigh Behnke - Artist's Statements and Other Writings, 1984-2009 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Writings About Leigh Behnke, undated; 1997 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subject Files (Box 6)
    - Cempellin, Leda, 2000-2005 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Charleston, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - City Oils, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Elaine Baker Gallery, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Elipse, circa 2002 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Exhibition Planning, circa 1997 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Fischbach Brochure, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Grant Applications, circa 1988 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Grant Applications, E. D. Foundation, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Hanbury Gate, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Information and Additions, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Lake Landscape (E. Baker), circa 2000 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Leigh (full packet), 2004 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Merchant House Museum, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Old Images, circa 1990s-circa 2005 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Painting Titles and Miscellaneous Printed Items, undated; 1990-1997 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Press Clippings, 1967-2006 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Projected Paintings, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Reference Information, etc., undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Reviews, Exhibition Announcements, and Miscellaneous Printed Items, 1978-1983 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Sagamore Hill, New Orleans, circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 34-35)
    - Walla Walla [Exhibition Installation Notes?], undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Printed Material (Box 6)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, undated; 1978-2008 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1974-2002 (Box 6, Folder 38-41)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Items, 1984-2008 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographic Materials (Box 7)
    - Leigh Behnke and Don Eddy, 1974; Oversized material housed in Box 9 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Artwork by Behnke, 1974; circa 1991-circa 2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Source Material, circa 1970s-circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 5-13)
    - Source Material, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
  - Oversized Photographs of Leigh Behnke from Box 7, Folder 3, circa 1980s-1996 (Box 9)